[Music]
w
good evening good day everybody and
welcome back to the ask Abhijit Show
episode
21208 I hope everybody is doing great
let's see who all is is there on the
live chat today I'm going to be taking
questions that you have asked in the
comments a bunch of those questions and
once that is done I will take questions
from the live chat as well so let's see
who all is there I can see Rainbow free
Soul
suar disappeared ravindra CH K viad RoR
shaswat mukarji gotami biplab data
special operator Kenneth tan from the
Philippines much love free Soul suar
chag Nala parer
bavan agent bod Bollywood V nandor mavin
Zub is good evening Annabeth Jackson
hello red winter Rangers wolf Aman Kumar
vikrant marati Vladimir pel hello rut
majumdar gorov ragav Gupta Vladimir
Abhijit chavda bishwajit L Karan nwat GK
javahar chavda Miguel Diaz adish jit m
Gupta rat Chopra Cosmic gaving 7781
Anita kup hello anant Pai LJ the man
Sati Chan hsh Kim Jong-un hello uh
molana dinosaur okay ad Raj tiari Ganesh
peral Roshan ja feminist Slayer Matrix
awaria D dkumar DK Raa Ain Tushar Mishra
an aish sarwal dihara Gupta just need
sing diit Vin Raj geopolitical dub LJ
the man Dr s alok p wiing
cam Mahesh pel ragunath mukarji Vikram
ADI space KGB agent Malik Sayad shagun
Chopra Aram Mana kadam Nishant innocent
boy chandan foram kacha Niha tomar and
everybody else all right all right all
right let's go ahead with the questions
that I have picked from the comments
we'll take a bunch of those and then we
will take questions from the live chat
so what do we have from the comments
let's find
out okay this is by sabir Ahmed uh
watching from New York enjoy your
analysis a lot thank you you are 100%
correct about the internal conflict
within Bangladeshi Society Bengali ethos
versus Islamic mindset unfortunately the
Islamic mindset is taking over and the
Pakistan 2.0 is in progress right so
yeah I think I had in one of the recent
live streams that
Bangladesh is conflicted deeply
conflicted just like Pakistan is De
deeply conflicted and it's a different
kind of conflict in Pakistan I mean it's
different yet similar so the Bengali the
Bangladeshi the conflict within
Bangladesh is a conflict between between
its ageold thousands of years old
Bengali ethos Bengali identity Indian ID
identity essentially and the more recent
Islamic mindset that's the conflict that
Bangladesh faces and it's it's a
fundamental conflict it's it's a
question about the very identity of
Bangladesh itself and the true identity
is the thousands of year old identity
which is the Indian Identity or the
Bengali identity that's in conflict with
the with the East Pakistani mindset
right Pakistan was based was was formed
on the basis of religion so that's
that's where that comes in the religious
angle and that's the situation right now
and right now it's very clear that
Pakistan is once again in the sorry
Bangladesh is once again in the process
of becoming of of of becoming East
Pakistan
again so that's the situation and there
is this well you can see an outpouring
of hatred towards India right now in
Bangladesh among many people I'm not
saying most people among many people and
that's all been inflamed by the
politicians and and the regime change
agents by by by by creating narratives
that people believe in so if you are a
patriotic person if you're a nationalist
nationalistic person and if you are told
that India this foreign external power
is interfering in the internal affairs
of Bangladesh and propping up this evil
dictator
lady then it will make your blood boil
especially when you pour in a hint of
religion from from behind
so that's the situation right now so
yeah Bangladesh is once again in the
process of becoming East Pakistan the
events of 1971 this who the the regime
change agents Etc they seek to undo
whatever happened in 1971 so that's
where Bangladesh is going and you can
see that very clearly with the fact in
the fact that the the the so-called
protesters the students Etc they have
been destroying statues of Sheik mujibur
Rahman the founding father of Bangladesh
right so he's the guy who was the face
of the new nation
Bangladesh right the first uh leader the
first Prime
Minister uh he is the guy who marked the
transition from East Pakistan to
Bangladesh and now they're destroying
his his statues his trying to erase his
legacy which means they're trying to
revert Bangladesh to the status of East
Pakistan so that is indeed something
that's in progress right now
uh another question or comments Abed
Mahmud says I have watched some of our
videos some of your videos and as a
Bengali from Bangladesh I've learned a
lot I feel Modi is stupid for not
uniting us it is US Bengali that's
scared of Alexander the Great India is
trying to divide us but we are one
people I hope you mentioned this more so
we can unite our leaders are absolutely
stupid the subcontinent doesn't need
anyone any other nation in the world if
including Myanmar if we in the
subcontinent unit is one we can go back
to right before the colonialism and
become even more powerful please share
this message with the audience we are
one people one nation we are only
divided because of the West yeah lots of
interesting uh aspects to unpack in this
we are indeed one people we are not one
nation in the in the sense of a nation
state we are one civilization and we
have historically been the same
civilization for thousands of years and
you are right we are divided because of
the West to serve a western agenda they
are the ones who divided the
subcontinent fragmented and balkanized
the subcontinent to serve their agenda
to serve their geopolitical objectives
that's why India was broken up into
pieces right in 1947 East Pakistan West
Pakistan before that Myanmar was taken
Burma was taken out in 1935 Sri Lanka
was separated Afghanistan happened
before a few centuries before but in
Nepal obviously never became part of
India it was no part of the British
Raj it was never officially annexed by
the British so that's how the
subcontinent was divided and this
artificial Nation Pakistan which is east
and west Pakistan it was created to
further the British or Western
geopolitical agenda in this overall
extended region which which uh it it
affects the geopolitical situation from
all the way from West Asia to Southeast
Asia because India the Indian
subcontinent occupies this
incredibly important strategic location
in Eurasia it dominates the Indian Ocean
region and and and much more it it
dominates the trade routes the shipping
routes and and all that so that's why
they divided the nation they broke up
the nation and to to justify the the
breaking up and partitioning of the
nation they created these these they
sword over decades these seeds of hatred
among the people of
India and they exhaust cated the the the
legacy of the turkey colonization of
India and they they are past Past
Masters Past Masters at doing this
divide and conquer divide and
Rule so that's the situation and right
now U Bangladesh obviously is a separate
country in 71 we had the chance to
reunite but our government in India
chose to not reunite bangl East Pakistan
or Bangladesh with the rest of India it
was out of India for just 24 years at
that stage but no it was given
Independence and since then a lot has
happened a lot of water has flown down
the bridge now is Mr Modi stupid for not
uniting us are our leaders absolutely
stupid look Mr Modi is currently not in
a position to
reunite uh the subcontinent or reunite
Bangladesh with
India first of all there is a very
strong anti-india sentim sentiment in
Bangladesh the right time to
reunite uh East Bengal with India or
east Pakistan with India was 71 it was
the perfect opportunity and at that time
there was no anti-india sentiment among
the people of of the region of of the of
the of of East Pakistan or Bangladesh
there was no anti-india sentiment at the
time but we chose not to
reunite our India's leadership chose not
to reunite Bangladesh with India
Bangladesh became a separate nation and
over the next 50 years the this the
anti-india sentiment has been slowly
built up and now the people of
Bangladesh most of them a large number
of them have a very strongly anti-india
sentiment so now is not the right time
you open the borders reunited there's
going to be communal clashes violence
riots whatnot Mass migration it's going
to be a disaster if we happen if we do
it right now what needs to happen is the
the the anti-india narrative that has
been that has been constructed over the
past 50 years needs to be essentially
defanged right but how does it happen
right now you have a strongly anti-india
government in power so it's going to be
strengthened right now so it's not the
right time for Mr Modi to reunite and
first of all even if he wants to reunite
the Bangladesh was with India how does
he do it because Bangladesh right now is
a US proxy it's a newly minted us proxy
State new newly minted US vasal state
the moment India tries to do anything
the Americans will will they are waiting
for an opportunity to
well impose sanctions on India or do
whatever they they they genuinely wish
to do Vis
India so uh that's where we are right
now there have been lots of
opportunities in the past that have been
missed by our leaders right now India is
not that powerful that it can stand up
to the US and do what it wants on the
subcontinent it was possible in 71
because India had the backing of the
USSR which was as powerful as the US
that's why it happened right now it's
mono it's a unipolar world the US is the
only superpower nobody can stand up to
it they're right now playing games in
Indonesia there's a regime change that's
going to happen in Indonesia as well
they are trying to upend the entire
region the extended subcontinent region
so uh yeah but overall we are the same
people no question about it no question
about it was it Bengali who scared of
Alexander the Great Well when Alexander
attempted
his in attemp attempted his hairbrained
invasion of India the nand dynasty the N
nand Empire was in power in India it was
based out of patut the capital was
patliputra and it's part of the extended
extended bangadesh region of of course
well patliputra was magad and south of
magad essentially you have bangadesh
this giant region and magad and and and
bangadesh definitely was part of the
nandha Empire as was most of the Indian
subcontinent so yes Bengali or the
people of Wanga were definitely part of
the
overall ethnicity or overall
civilization or military force that
scared of Alexander the Great soldiers
they refused to to Step One to take one
step further eastwards they knew what
was awaiting them they would have been
annihilated by the military might of the
nand
Empire so yeah that's the deal so I hope
we reunite in the future but we have to
reunite on our terms as in us the people
of the subcontinent and we cannot
reunite in a when there's a situation
where there's a significant amount of
hostility towards India in Bangladesh we
can't reunite at the time because that's
going to cause incredible
chaos so it's going to be a while before
this happens but
look if this is this period of time is
an aberration in the history of the
subcontinent we historically have been
one and we're going to revert to the
default settings sooner or later for
that India is going to have to rise
economically militarily Etc and that's
the direction India is headed do us and
that's why the West wants to impede
India's growth so that is where we are
right now in 2024 but I appreciate your
comments and the sentiments you
express okay let's talk about Mr Mod's
recent visit to
Ukraine so a number of questions here
why is Prime Minister Modi visiting
Ukraine is he being pre pressurized to
do so how do Washington DC and Moscow
see Modi G's Ukraine visit U yeah and
what's the impact of Narendra Modi sir
traveling to Ukraine what's going to be
the response of Russia China and the US
so the main question is why has Mr Modi
prime minister of India visited Ukraine
he concluded visit yesterday he's back
today or whenever he came back he's
already back in India as far as I know
so it was a brief visit he visited Kev
he met with Mr zelinsky gave him a hug
and put his hand on on his shoulder then
there were some some agreements signed
and then Mr zalinski lectured India and
condemned India for buying oil from
Russia and demanded that India become
Pro West Pro Ukraine Etc so Mr Modi goes
to Ukraine meets zalinsky and then Mr
zalinsky gives Mr Modi a lecture okay a
sanctimonious lecture that's essentially
what
happened so why did Mr Modi visit
Ukraine first of all look we have to
understand that uh India's foreign
policy what is the purpose of India's
foreign policy and foreign engagements
engagements with other countries the
purpose is to serve India's national
interest right to serve and further
India's national interest that's that is
supposed to be the only objective of any
nation's foreign policy including
India's so now we have to ask ourselves
in what way does Mr modi's visit to
Ukraine serve or further India's
national
interest the only thing I can come up
with is that the Ukraine war which
started in 2022 February this war has
depressed the economy of Europe it has
sent a
few European economies into recession
and overall it's it's kind of depressed
the overall economy of the western world
and India needs to grow economically we
know that we need to keep growing for
the next 20 years 30 years if you want
to become a middle income nation and a
great power so if half the world's
economy or more than half the world's
economy is depressed then it's not good
for our economy because we need to trade
with them we need to export things to
them and get money from them and so on
so forth we need to engage economically
and if their econom is not doing well
our economy also will suffer to a
certain extent as a result or maybe to
large extent so we want the Western
economy to start doing well again and
the major trigger that depressed the
Western economy European economy Etc was
the Ukraine war the northstream 2 thing
and the cutting off of Russian gas
supplies to to Germany and so on so
forth lots of factors involved in there
so hopefully if the Ukraine war ends or
there's a ceasefire or some kind of
negotiated settlement then maybe the
European economy will start doing better
again and it will help India's economy
as well so
that's the
long that's the that's the thing one can
think of that maybe Mr Modi has gone to
Ukraine to offer India's good offices uh
as a as as a mediator between East and
West because India is uniquely
positioned to serve as a bridge between
East and West if both sides so desire
India has a great amount of comfort and
trust with Russia India has a great
amount of comfort and trust with the
West as well so we can mediate and
hopefully get both sides to the
negotiating on the negotiating table and
hopefully bring about a negotiated end
or or ceasefire to the war that's the
farfetched scenario one can think of
which could serve or further India's
national interest now the West doesn't
want to negotiate we know that Putin has
been saying for a long time let's let's
negotiate let's let's go
and sit on a table and and do diplomacy
and negotiate the West doesn't want
that so this is a far-fetched scenario
okay
so why has then so it's it's almost
inconceivable that the West wants to
negotiate with Russia U it's it's
probably not going to happen and you
have the US election coming up very soon
the presidential election what and if Mr
Trump comes to power there may be some
chance of negotiation but would he want
India to be involved or not we don't
know about that so there's a lot of ifs
and buts and lots of factors in this so
the scenario I am presenting to you that
India may it may serve India's national
interest interest to act as a mediator
between east and west and eventually
bring about the end of the Ukraine war
it's a very farflung far-fetched
scenario but that's the only scenario
which I can think of that serves the
Indian national
interest is there any other factor that
would have caused Mr Modi to visit
Ukraine well
pressure pressure yeah
look Mr Modi recently visited Moscow he
met with Mr Putin right and we have good
excellent relations with Moscow the West
doesn't like it we have refused to come
on board with the Western sanctions on
Russia the West doesn't like it we have
been purchasing very large quantities of
Russian oil the West doesn't like it and
the West recently the Americans recently
engineered a regime change operation in
Bangladesh and and propped up a very
strongly anti-india government right in
India's neighborhood in India's
backyard they already have engineered a
coup in Pakistan which people don't even
realize was a coup the out of Imran Khan
who was Pro China and now we have a very
strongly Pro US government in Pakistan
as well India is being encircled now
there's a regime change operation
unfolding in
Indonesia right now student protests etc
etc same old
Playbook
so the Americans have the ability to to
engineer regime change anywhere they
want
okay so they would have I assure you
they would have pressurized India they
would have pressurized Mr Modi to go and
visit Ukraine and then Mr Modi has to go
there and he has to listen to zinsky
lecturing him and condemning India and
criticizing
India did did did that serve India's
national interest no but it did that you
you you exceeded to the American demands
and that would to some extent for some
time mify them per perhaps the
Americans so how will Washington DC see
this visit of Mr Modi to Ukraine they'll
see it as as a win that we got Modi to
do whatever we wanted we demanded this
and he had
to compromise and he had to exceed to
our demand so they can see that there is
more room for pressurizing India now as
compared to before because Mr Modi now
is heading a coalition government he is
not all powerful he's a diminished prime
minister he's a weaker prime minister
the Americans can pressurize the various
political Coalition Partners in the
India government and they could actually
bring the government down the Americans
are capable of doing that so now Mr Modi
is more vulnerable to American pressure
you understand that's how the world
works the Americans will see this as a
win it will see they will see this as
validation of the fact that they can
pressurize India and they will use this
as the opportunity to pressurize India
more and interfere more in India's
Internal Affairs it's coming it's coming
my friends it's coming um how will
Moscow see Mr modi's Ukraine visit
Moscow will see it as something the
Putin will understand why Mr Modi had to
do it you will understand that the US is
more leverage over India you'll
understand that Modi will that this
visit will not really make India Pro
West or Pro ukine it's something just
India was pressurized into doing and
it's not going to fundamentally affect
in any way the relationship between
India and
Russia how will China see this they will
see it exactly the way Russia sees it
and China is also under tremendous
pressure from the US by the way so
that's where we are we have been
pressurized into doing this it does not
serve India's national interest in any
significant way okay but it's a if you
want to put it nicely you can say that
this was a curtsy visit by Mr Modi to
Ukraine and Mr zinsky did not behave
well he lectured Prime Minister Modi and
criticized and condemned India when he
should there was no for him to do that
but there you are that's what you have
so is this uh does it mean that Mr Modi
has has you know is this a loss for Mr
mod it's not a loss it's just the game
that you have to play you got to play
this when you are weaker you compromise
when you get stronger can be more
resilient that's how it goes so you got
to do what's best in the long run for
your country and probably this is the
right thing to do
okay Atul esbat says Ukraine claims to
control a, square kilometers of Russian
territory the Kursk region Kur oblast in
the biggest incursion since the second
world war is it a victory and a
bargaining bet for Ukraine comments
please okay let's go to the map and find
out what on Earth is happening in this
region yes so we let's go to Ukraine
okay the map is all skewed around so
let's go to Ukraine it's north of the
Black Sea and if you go eastwards of
Ukraine we have the
uh
Kursk where is
Kur where is Kursk oh here we are here
is Kursk so they seem to have or they
claim to be in control of some amount of
Russian territory maybe a th000 square
kilometers or something that's the claim
now we have no way ofing whether this
claim is correct but assuming this claim
is correct they are currently in control
let's say we assume that this claim is
correct that they currently control a
th000 square kilometers of Russian
territory is this a victory for Ukraine
let me tell you let me ask you a
different question in February 22 Russia
went ahead and took donet it took
luhansk it took maruul it was it took
Kon was that a victory for Russia in the
Ukraine war they had Advanced all the
way Russian tanks had Advanced all the
way to the outskirts of Kiev was that a
a victory for
Russia the Russians had taken karv was
it a victory for Russia they took karv
and the to they went out uh they took uh
Kon and then they retreated uh they were
on the on the outskirts of UK of of Kiev
and they retreated so was that a victory
or a loss for for Russia the ukra
ukrainians uh lost so much territory is
that a loss for Ukraine have they lost
the
war um there were so many other battles
that happened uh so the war is
ongoing this is a temporary situation in
the war this is not the end of the war a
victory or a defeat is something that
signals the end of a war this is a phase
of the
war
right uh
so it's it's a situation that's
happening happened and the Russians as
you may be aware are tremendously more
powerful than the
ukrainians so I think even if Ukraine
let's say the let's say the situation is
correct and the ukrainians control
currently 1,000 square kilometers of
Russian territory how long do you think
it'll last how long do you think it'll
last have the are the ukra are the
Russians even using a significant amount
of their assets do you even know the
kind of Firepower the Russians have
so I think it's a situation that's
evolving it's been evolving since
February 2022 there have been lines on
the map that have been constantly
changing going backwards forward
everything and this is some this is just
part of that it is not a victory or a
defeat by any means on for this side or
the other it is an evolu evolving phase
of the
war is that a bargaining bet for Ukraine
why don't they try to bargain and then
see what happen happens I mean so look
you cannot keep on commenting about
everything that happens every week or
every five days
Ukraine because that's what that's what
Indian TV channels do okay there's an
advance by Russia or Ukraine 10
kilometers they will dissect that in
great detail and have 20 panelists come
and discuss that that's a an exercise in
futility and pointlessness look at the
bigger picture zoom out zoom out zoom
out look at the bigger picture what is
Russia's what are Russia's objectives
what are NATO's objectives that what
that's what you would understand in that
context you have to decide whether it's
a victory or a loss and right now
there's no the war is still ongoing so
Russia's objectives are to den naify
Ukraine turn Ukraine into a
genuinely permanently neutral nation and
effect a regime change in Kev that's
Russia's objectives what are NATO's
objectives NATO's objectives are to
destroy Russia okay essentially and and
effect a regime change in
Moscow now has any side achieved any of
these objectives no is the war still
going on yes so how is it a victory how
is it a
loss it's it's an evolution it's it's
it's a passing phase of the conflict
that's what it
is okay Harel Agarwal says what is
happening in Indonesia is it Another
Blessing of Uncle Sam or is it this time
the the dragon the dragon
China so let's find out what's happening
what is the what are the news reports
like what what do the news reports say
about
Indonesia so let's see what the
Americans have to say Voice of America
Voice of America this news report is
from yesterday August 23 2024 protesters
rally again as Tempest flare over
Indonesia political
Maneuvers so University students SL
shout slogans during a protest against
the move to overturn a constitutional
Court ruling that change eligibility
rules for candidates in the general
election later this year in band AE
Indonesia and so on and so forth so
thousands of people have rallied in
several cities in Indonesia pressurizing
its Election Commission to issue rules
for regional voting amst outrage outrage
by whom over an attempt by parliamentary
allies of pres president Joko to change
the rules in their favor so what's
happened is that joku vido has lost the
election and his current defense
minister has won the election and I
forget the name of the defense minister
but he's going to take charge take take
power as president of Indonesia around
October this
year now the defense minister is well he
is Joko with those current defense
minister so kind of on the same side
right and the some rules have been
changed which allow Mr vdo's son to to
be part of things and all that that sort
of thing and
the the incoming new president the
current defense
minister is a nationalist his portrait
is a nationalist right- Wier and he's in
favor of an independent foreign policy a
non- Alliant foreign policy let's say
for indon Indonesia and his favor of
good ties with
Russia now that is very naughty if you
are if you're America very naughty
behavior that is not acceptable so what
do you do regime change of operation so
that's what we are seeing here now let's
see another news
report uh let's put that on the screen
give me a
second right so what are the students
saying this is the Straits times we
cannot remain silent students at Ward of
Indonesian protests amid worries about
democracy Jovi is a mistake it's
apparently a city in West Java they are
gathering outside Indonesia's Parliament
complex yesterday in Jakarta
um so apparently so so what's being this
this situation is Port being portrayed
as uh students fighting for democracy
and Jovi is is is an
authoritarian uh undemocratic leader so
naturally students are the good guys and
they have to do things like these right
uh this is the BBC one another Another
Western
publication police clash with protesters
over Indonesia LW change and you can
read the thing and Jakarta BL blah now
let us see another one another okay this
is from temp
tempo.co DPR kpu assure Regional
election law etc
etc one second that's not the
one okay this one Indonesian student
protesters occupy DPR complex to secure
MK ruling the DPR complex is the
Parliamentary complex of Indonesia so
they are occupying the Parliamentary
complex in Jakarta hundreds of student
protesters defending the decision of the
Constitutional Court entered the
frontyard of the Parliamentary complex
as the demonstration turned chaotic on
Thursday two days before today they
began to enter the courtyard through a
broken fence near the main gate Western
time the crowd who rushed in and
occupied the front yard and apparently
the the police or or whatever could not
do anything about this sounds eily
similar to
Bangladesh um and so on so forth chaos
etc etc etc okay so that is the
situation in Indonesia so the current
Indonesian government is kind of has a
mind of its own and wants an independent
foreign policy wants a non-aligned
foreign policy which means we take our
decisions we don't need anyone's advice
or anyone's lectures and they are okay
with a good relationship with Russia
which is no no no no no no from the
American eyes from the American
perspective so then what is happening in
Indonesia makes sense naturally right so
it's a blessing from Uncle Sam now if
you look back at the history of
Indonesia Indonesia becomes independent
what 1930 something whatever whichever
year it is and president sukarno takes
power and then president sukarno is oued
in a military coup and who's the guy who
who's the ring leader of the coup
president suaro
president suaro oued sukarno in a coup
which year was it uh okay let's go and
Google it which year because I don't
have dates
memorized like Indian students
unfortunately
suaro
soar so he took off he took power in
1968 and he Unleashed Unleashed mass
killings at
Etc as soon like like before he took
power and he was he was kind of like his
his coup was an outcome of these mass
killings and all that the reign of
terror which was supposedly an
anti-communist thing okay it was
supposedly to to eliminate Communists
because Communists are evil so who was
going after the Communists in the 1950s
6070s Etc during the Cold War the
Americans were going after this so suaro
was an American agent it was a US
mediated regime change it was a horrible
blood bath in Indonesia horrible
absolutely horrible and
then suaro ruled until what the 90s or
something and then other people came to
power and Jovi is probably the first
non- US puppet most likely to be in
power so that's not a good situation and
the US is trying to rectify things so
you're going to have a regime change
most likely in Indonesia as well the
same way it happened in Bangladesh
student protests and eventually the the
situation becomes untenable and then a
US blessed regime comes to power and the
Indonesian version of Muhammad yunus may
come to power or maybe or maybe to
prevent such a thing from happening the
current government may become more pro
pro
us that may also happen so you give in
you you bend the knee you kiss the ring
and then you do what the Americans say
and then there is no regime change and
the student protests die out
magically so that's what's happening in
Indonesia the Americans are trying to
completely reconfigure the political map
of the entire extended subcontinental
region I mean you got to admire the
Americans for what they can achieve they
completely encircled India China Chinese
occupied debate Etc is not obviously Pro
us it's entirely anti-
us but there you have it so if Indonesia
again becomes very strongly Pro us
Malaysia is already strongly Pro us then
once again the Americans can blockade
the malaka strait you see the malaka
strait is of vital importance the
Americans will soon have an island of
their own the St Martin's St Lawrence
whatever it's called St whatever St
Martin's Island which belongs to
Bangladesh the Americans will soon take
over establish a military base there
they will have an artificial Nation
called cookie land def facto Nation uh
Bangladesh is pro us and now Indonesia
one way or the other will once again
become a pro us
nation and then the malaka strait is
Theirs to control
America you got to admire that really
that's how you do it that's how you
exercise project power and exercise the
power that you have or various
Nations Sun Moon
0877 yeah says why does Poland not allow
allow immigrants since Poland is part of
the European
Union the EU has this policy that when
people from certain Paths of the world
come in apparently as refugees and apply
for political asylum in EU member
nations then these European Union
Nations must accept them as long as they
are from certain religions and certain
countries okay and then uh these
refugees should be redistributed all
across the European Union Nations that's
the kind of thing they have and if a
certain Nation does not want these
immigrants then they need to pay I don't
know how many dollars per immigrant
maybe 10,000 or $20,000 20,000 Euros I
believe per immigrant that is not
allowed or something like that so if if
10 immigrants are refused entry by a
nation they have to pay the European
Union €200,000
and if 100 immigrants are not allowed by
a nation then they have to pay the
European union2 million EUR and so on so
forth so the European Union assigns
quotas to Every Nation these nations
have to
accept and host these refugees who
generally are military age men from
Western Asian Nations or Afghanistan or
Iraq or whatever or certain African
nations and they never go back right so
that's how the demography of the
European European Union is being
permanently changed altered on orders
from Brussels which is controlled from
Washington that's what's happening now
there are two Nations Poland and Hungary
that disagree with this and they are not
allowing immigrants when it comes to
Poland let's let's take a look at where
where Poland is on the
map so where is Poland let's go to the
map the Poland is east of Ukraine sorry
west of Ukraine right Poland is west of
Ukraine and west of Belarus so
Poland is a nation that has a policy of
selective
immigration they have accepted more than
a million refugees from Ukraine but they
have refused to accept refugees from
West Asia or
Africa and they say that there are
National Security issues and sovereignty
issues so we will decide who comes in
and who doesn't come in which should be
right but the deal with the EU is that
when you become a member of the EU
you give up some of your sovereignty you
have to lose some of your sovereignty as
a member of the EU and Poland doesn't
want to lose that sovereignty neither
does
Hungary and they don't want to pay Their
fines either so they're in this dicey
situation so Poland is doing this to
safeguard their demographic Integrity
their ethnic Integrity their cultural
Integrity in overall their sovereignty
they're doing that to safegard their
sovereignty and their the Integrity of
the nation that's why they don't allow
immigrants
let's see how long this situation is is
able to continue how long they're able
to keep
refusing uh because the EU is much more
powerful than Poland but Poland is an
important Nation because Poland is Right
west of Ukraine if hypothetically
Ukraine sooner or later loses the war to
Russia then NATO says that Russia will
then take try to take over Poland and
other nations West because they claim
that Russia wants to expand is a
hegemonic expansionist nation so after
Ukraine it will be the turn of Poland
Etc so Poland is the next bulwark for
the for the for Western Europe so Poland
is militarizing they are they already
have more tanks than Germany they
already have more artillery pieces
howitzers ET than Germany they are
spending I don't know maybe around 10
billion dollar purchasing arms amunition
from South Korea from the US Etc F35
fighter planes more than a thousand
tanks roughly a thousand tanks from
South Korea fighter planes from South
Korea train of trainer planes from South
Korea and much more Poland is very
important so Poland May that's maybe
that's the reason why the the pools are
able to perhaps get away with this
intransigent attitude of not bending the
knee when it comes to immigration but
let's see how long that lasts so that is
the
situation sh bunel says if Russia values
its relations with India why does it
still engage with Pakistan they invited
Imran Khan to Russia on the eve of the
incursion yes February
2022 when when did this special military
operation start Ukraine I think 24th of
February 2022 I believe if my memory
serves me right sometime in February and
this happened while Imran Khan was in
Moscow and he was caught completely
unawares and that that was a very bad
look for him and very soon after that he
he was purged he was he he offered a
coup a regime change operation and
somebody else came to part I don't know
who who's the Prime Minister currently
in Pakistan one of the Sharif guys I
think Mia shabas Sharif believe I
believe whoever it is it's the army that
rules Pakistan but they got rid of Imran
Khan so the deal is the question is
about Russia not about Imran Khan so
what's the deal between Russia and
Pakistan you see in the 2010s the
Russians had stepped up their engagement
had ramped up their engagement with
Pakistan they had sold Pakistan a number
of military helicopters okay they were
also engaging in yearly military
exercises with Pakistan the Duba
exercises Duba is a Russian word which
means
friendship so Russia was engaging in
yearly friendship military exercises
military training exercises with
Pakistan and this went on from what 2017
2018 2019 all the way to 2020 1 and then
mysteriously in 2022 there was no Duba
exercise and there there hasn't been
any Duba exercise since
2021 it stopped in in 22 it was supposed
to happen in 22 didn't happen why is
that I I wonder why is that it's because
there was a regime change in Pakistan
Pakistan becomes a us wasal again and
Russia because of the Ukraine special
military operation needed India's help
needed on its side so that's why all
those that that diance with Pakistan
ended with the Pakistani military ended
so you see international relations
that's how it works it's all about
personal interest it's all about
National
interest my interest comes first you may
have been my friend for 500 years but
now you no longer serve my interest so
I'll find other friends that's how it
goes even Russia
was dallying with Pakistan right
and right now Pakistan is a member of
the Shanghai cooperation
organization uh and
uh what's the deal with
them Shanghai cooperation organization
they certainly are a part of that and
Pakistan wants to become a member of
bricks I
believe and they would like Russia to to
allow them to have this happen there's a
lot
happening and uh this year's uh SEO
Summit will happen most likely in in in
in Russia St Petersburg and the Pakistan
is are going to pressurize Russia to
allow them to enter bricks and various
other things are going on so the
pakistanis are still trying to PT
Russia and it's up to Russia to do what
it wants and to decide which
relationship is more
important because if they go ahead with
Pakistan it's not going to go well with
India for sure and India certainly has
options so you see it's all about these
calculations in international relations
in geopolitics India and the USSR had a
great relationship well it served both
Nations purposes that's why the
relationship was great it was founded on
shared interests it was not about all
love and hugs and shared values it's
never about shared values it's always
about shared
interests Russia and Pakistan had have
no shared values
but they were engaging together for a
while India and Russia may have some
shared values for sure but it's more
about interests than values you know
when the Americans talk about their
relationship with India they they play
up the shared values we have shared
values with India we
are democratic nations so on so forth
when the Americans talk about their
relationship with Pakistan they talk
about shared interests and I promise you
interests Trump values which tells you
that the American relationship with
Pakistan is stronger than their
relationship than the American
relationship with India that's how it
goes uh so right now Russia will not
engage that M with Pakistan and they
will be wise not to I would say because
look they've got to work together with
India we have shared
interests there's much more overlap of
interests between Russia and India than
Russia and Pakistan I mean no question
about it so there you have
it rudrajit sarar says 80% of mova
citizens are ethnically
Romanian then why is mova not part of
Romania is good question yes let's let's
look into this so where is mova first of
all so
it's in Eastern Europe okay you know the
Ukraine war is Raging so if you go to
Ukraine you go to the South E Southwest
of Ukraine you have this nation called
mova and the capital is chisha this is
the capital of
mova now the question is and you are
right that the majority of the citizens
of mova are ethnic
Romanians so why is mova not part of
Romania is the question so now let's
understand
this you know there used to be something
called the Ottoman
Empire the Ottoman Empire was you could
say the successor state of the Byzantine
Empire they destroyed the Byzantine
Empire the Turks and they conquered this
entire land Anatolia and th Etc and they
established an Empire here and it was a
massive Empire it it uh it
conquered most of Arabia it
conquered uh much of North Africa and
and significant parts of Eastern Europe
so the Balkan region was was under the
Ottoman Empire and there's still all the
Balan nonsense that goes on is a legacy
of the Ottoman occupation of the region
so Albania Bosnia Serbia Croatia etc etc
was all part of the Ottoman Empire and
obviously so was Greece so was Romania
and so on so that's the background that
mova was then part of the of of the
principality of the region of mold dvia
it was part of the Ottoman Empire now in
the early 19th century there were
conflicts which were ongoing between the
Ottoman Empire and the Russian Empire
and Russia defeated the Ottomans and
took over the the this principality of
Moldavia um then after the end of the
first world war Moldavia becomes part of
Romania it became part of Romania what
198 18 or thereabouts 1918 or
thereabouts
then there is the second world war that
happens there is the molotov rrop pact
between Nazi Germany and the USSR and as
part of that the USSR takes over the
Western the eastern part of the
principality of Moldavia which becomes
the mova SSR Soviet Socialist
Republic and then this entire region
this this present the country of mova
becomes part of the
USSR and it
is
rified uh
they they they are made to speak a a
certain form of
Romanian which is the movan language and
the script that they made to use is the
cilic script the script in which you
write the Russian language so that
situation persists from the 19 late
1930s early 1940s all the way to
1991 when the USSR breaks up so when the
USSR breaks up mova declares
independence and it is recognized by the
UN Etc blah blah blah as as an
independent Sovereign
Nation so that's how it becomes an
independent Sovereign Nation that is
separate from Romania and by that time
it has its own separate identity with
its uh seric script and and so on and so
forth and then there is also the
transnistria uh conflict that is going
on that I have spoken about I have a
video at least one video on this channel
about the transnistria
conflict and the capital of transnistria
is thas it is you could say de facto
Russian exclave and so on so that is the
reason why mova is a separate nation
despite most be most of its the majority
of its citizens being ethnic Romanians
they now the during during the period of
time that they were part of the USSR
they developed a distinct
identity and there have been demands to
reintegrate mova with with Romania but
after 91 it's been recognized as as as
an independent Sovereign Nation that's
what it has remained like and it has
kind of a slightly different and
slightly distinct identity from Romania
today even though ethnically they are
the same and linguistically they very
similar so that is a deal with mova
rudrajit sarar again asks about Napoleon
a question about Napoleon what were
Napoleon's views towards India and
Indians look Napoleon did not know much
about India as such about India's
culture and history and all that for
Napoleon India was an important
geographical region and Napoleon's
number one enemies were the British the
British Empire and he his overall agenda
was to bring about the downfall of the
British Empire and establish the
Napoleonic Empire let's take a look at
the map to understand what was going on
so Napoleon was born in Cora K it is
called yes this this island here uh AO
or whatever the name is and then he
became French he dabbled with the
thought of becoming uh British but long
story so he becomes the emperor of
France in Italy and he wanted to become
the global superpower essentially and
establish a very large empire and he
wanted to defeat the British Empire the
British were his number one enemies and
that was why he invaded
Egypt and for him it was very important
to end British rule in India because
India was a very major source of wealth
and what not for the British and he knew
that there were there was the sentiment
in
India for regaining Independence and
ending the brutal British occupation of
India he knew that so his invasion of
Egypt was intended to be a stepping
stone towards his invasion of India so
he wanted to invade India eventually and
establish his rule there and evict the
British from India and then he would
plunder India just the way the British
would okay and he made an alliance with
the Butcher of myor Tipo Sultan the the
horrible Tyrant and he didn't care
whether he was a bad Tyrant or whatever
he just wanted allies powerful allies
who were ruling India and tipu tipu the
Butcher of myour was fighting the
British he was fighting against the
British not for India's independence for
but for his own sovereignty right so
that he could continue doing whatever he
was doing so that's why Napoleon
established uh an alliance with tipu and
I believe he sent messages and letters
and uh diplomatic embassies to other
Indian rulers as well but the alliance
that he made was with tipu
but uh it's around uh 1798 to 1801 or
something thereabouts that he tried to
invade Egypt and he failed he was
defeated eventually and he had to limp
back to Italy and that's that's kind of
where his downfall slowly
begins and that's why nothing really
came out of it so his entire approach
towards India was
strategic it was based out of
self-interest he had a strategic
interest in India and he regarded India
as as the lynchpin of the British Empire
the source of the majority of the wealth
correctly of the British
Empire and he sought to establish his
own rule there he had as far as I know
no understanding of or no interest in
India's culture and therefore his his
his interest in India was purely driven
out of self-interest and out of
strategic
needs there you have
it and another question by rodra sarar I
have come across certain information
that says that chhatrapati shivaji
Maharaj abolished slavery from India in
n in
1645 what made him which made him the
first king in the world to abolish
slavery how far is this true and what's
your take on this okay so Shiva
chhatrapati shivaji
Maharaj was born I think in 16 1630
right so it can't couldn't have been in
1645 it was just 15 then I think he EST
he abolished slavery in his kingdom I
think in the late
1670s I think 1677 or something around
that time and uh by the time he had
conquered and and and liberated from the
Turks uh the region of Maharashtra and
and other and some parts of Southern
India as well so if you look at the map
uh the region of Maharashtra and parts
of present day Tamil Nadu uh Karnataka
Andra Etc he had liberated from the
Turks and it's around 1677 I believe
that he uh he officially abolished or
prohibited anybody from engaging in the
slave trade and and transporting slaves
and owning slaves because before he took
over the and liberated the region this
region was ruled by the Turks by the
various uh turkic Invaders and occupiers
of India and and also the Europeans to
some extent and the Europeans and the
Turks believed in slavery and they they
engaged in the buying and selling and
transportation of
slaves so once shivaji Maharaj took over
this large reasonably large region he
officially abolished the slavery and he
told everybody that no more buying
buying selling or transporting of slaves
nobody is allowed to own another human
being blanket abolition which probably
makes him the first king in as far as
the Western world is concerned in
recorded history to abolish slavery so
that is true it makes him the first to
abolish slavery so indeed true and uh
then the question will arise that do we
have slavery in India we did have
slavery in India when India was under
foreign occupation under turkic
occupation and European occupation the
Turks and the Europeans did engage in
the practice of slavery as we know very
well they believed in
slavery and they practiced slavery uh so
India had slavery when it was under
foreign occup
Turks and Europeans we never had a
native practice of slavery never ever
ever ever never it's not part of Indian
culture or civilization it goes under
against the very ethos of Indian culture
so India has never had
slavery
never
right kushagra Kalashnikov that's quite
a name says had India not been invaded
at all
would we have become colonizers could
there be an alternate relative reality
where India colonized Africa America and
maybe even
Europe okay so in the hypothetical
scenario that India had never been
invaded by either the Turks or the
Europeans would India would we have
become
colonizers what do we mean by
colonization is what we have to
understand first of all we have to ask
ourselves what do we mean by
colonization
colonization in the currently understood
context or perspective is the Islamic
and and Christian version of
colonization which is either settler
colonialism or extraction
colonialism what is extraction
colonialism you take over a
country enslave it defeat it occupy it
enslave it and extract everything of
value out of it that is extractive
colonization that's what the Turks did
out of India they various raids even
when the Turks
were occupying India by residing in it
they were sending a lot of wealth out of
India tremendous amount of wealth out of
India they were doing that when the
Europeans came to India and and occupied
parts of India and the British
eventually occupied all of India their
only purpose was extraction of wealth
and resources the only purpose so that
is extractive
colonization to beggar the country that
you're colonizing to to reduce the the
people to beggar Hood and the British
did conduct a genocide in India no doubt
even the Turks the turky genocide was
even more massive than the British
induced genocide now so that is
extractive colonization the other form
of colonization is settler colonization
which means
you you steal the land of the natives so
what's happened in Australia settler
colonization a superior race what they
believe that they are a superior race
the Europeans the British they came and
took over this entire continent and
essentially Enslaved the natives and
turned them into third class citizens
which they still
are in Tasmania they entirely wiped out
the native population in New Zealand the
natives are essentially second class
citizens right that is settler
colonization the the Europeans came and
stole the entire land and settled in it
and reduced the natives to second or
third class status if they were allowed
to survive at all if we look at the
Americas the same thing
happened between 50 to 100 million
Native Americans were killed in North
America over a certain time period and
today the natives of North America are
second class
citizens right they live on reservations
in terrible conditions and they have no
say in in in their future and it is the
settlers who rule the land the settlers
settlers are the Europeans and the same
thing essentially H is going on in South
America that is settler colonization the
colonizers did not have the objective of
stealing the resources extracting the
resources and the wealth their objective
was to steal the land
itself so that's the two forms of
colonization that we can think of
extractive colonization and secular
colonization
now does
this synchronize or does this align with
India's cultural
ethos extracting wealth out of a country
or a land and beggaring the locals
turning them into
Beggars or simply stealing the
land of another nation and reducing the
locals to second class status it does
not
align with
India's civilizational and cultural
values so Indians historically before
colon before we became colonized we were
Travelers we were a supremely maritime
Nation Indians there is evidence of
Indians
settling or at least having a presence
in
Australia 5,000 years before today
roughly okay and there is no evidence
that Indians colonized Australia or or
extracted anything out of Australia but
about if you look at the uh DNA of the
Aboriginal people the the true natives
of Australia about 10% of the DNA is of
Indian origin which means Indians came
there settled down and intermingled
intermarried with the locals and became
the
locals that's what happened now India
has a has a very old history of of uh
contacts with southeast Asia so we Bui
and Beyond Indonesia all the way up to
Japan
Etc and if you look at uh Cambodia for
example and you look at genetic studies
of the people of of the population of
Cambodia they have about four to 5%
Indian DNA so once again Indians settled
there but did not colonize did not
extract did not do anything like that
Thailand Myanmar everywhere you have
Indian DNA but Indians never stole the
land or stole the resources even when
our um we even when the Chola Empire
invaded and conquered much of Southeast
Asia nothing was ever stolen or
extracted and there was no theft of land
once again of course there was there
were Indians settling in the region in
small numbers which is why the people of
Indonesia have Indian DNA but there was
no takeover of the country or or or
extraction of wealth Indians have been
they are known to have
settled all across
East Africa way before the Europeans
ever knew what East Africa is but once
again Indians never extracted anything
and never stole the land the Indians
were Traders and
Merchants same thing with southeast Asia
and so on and I could go on and on okay
but it it's not conceivable that India
would have ever become a colonizing
culture or colonizing civilization there
is no alternate reality in which India
would have colonized Africa America or
anything Indians would have traveled
everywhere
and I'm sure they did in the past I'm
sure our people traveled all over the
world in the past and much of that
evidence may not be uh known right now
but it may exist somewhere if if one
were to search for it we know about
Africa we know about Australia we know
about Egypt we know about West Asia we
know about Eurasia we know about China
we know about Japan the question is did
Indians reach the Americas that's a real
question Europe and all we would know
that we had ties Africa Eurasia
everywhere Eastern Asia the question is
the Americas but even if we did reach
there we did not ever
colonize some of us may have settled
there so that's the deal there is no
alternate reality in which India would
have colonized other lands Indians would
have had contacts they would have done
trade they would they would have settled
there in small numbers but Indians were
never extractive Indians were
never Hees of land never
the question by kushagra Kal Kalashnikov
what are your thoughts on guns I think
the second amendment makes a lot of
sense the idea that a society in which
only the ones with guns are the cops is
kind of terrifying because if the
government goes tyrannical you crw could
it work in India so first of all let's
ask ourselves what is this second
amendment that kushagra Kalashnikov
speaks about so let's go to Google and
it's it's the Second Amendment of the US
Constitution that he's talking about so
let's let's search for it Second
Amendment all right that's it so you're
talking about the US
Constitution and let's see what
Wikipedia has to say because in this
case they're going to be accurate the
second com Amendment of the United
Constitution protects the right to keep
and bear arms it was ratified in
December 1791 and so on so
forth uh it
uh uh the the right belongs to
individuals for their self-defense in
the home while also including as dicted
the right is not unlimited and does not
preclude blah blah blah blah blah blah
blah blah blah blah blah etc etc etc so
it's about the right to keep and bear
arms that's what the US that's what the
Second Amendment to the US Constitution
is about and that's what the Americans
fight for you know there there's this
constant demand to to prevent to
prohibit Americans from private citizens
from owning and and bearing
arms and obviously you have the
situation there are all these massacres
in the US shootings public shootings
school shootings and all that so that's
a terrible situation in the US and then
the situation and the solution that's
been proposed is that the Americans
American citizens should not be allowed
to bear arms right so there the pros and
the cons the why is it necessary for why
do the Americans see it as necessary
that they should have the right to bear
arms it's because there's always a
threat that the government may become
tyrannical in which case what's what
what will the common citizen do they
need the right to self-defense so that
is the argument in favor of the right to
bear arms to keep and bear arms and the
argument against it is that then you can
have the situations you know mass
shootings and whatnot which happens in
the US and the question is why does it
happen in the US when not in other
nations if you look at a nation like
Switzerland where
everybody mostly everyone has arms
nothing happens no such no such
situation exists school shootings mass
shootings ET nothing Israel I'm pretty
sure everybody has arms no nothing
there and there are many other nations
where people have the right to bear arms
to have to have private ownership of
arms and these things don't happen why
only the US so there is something
peculiar about the
US okay and I'll not go into the details
why it happens so there you have it so
that's the second amendment the the
right to own and bear arms and carry
arms now in India in Barat until 19
until
1857 every Indian citizen had the right
to carry arms typically that would be
spear swords um bows arrows whatever
right so Indians had the right to carry
arms for self-defense and whatever else
we had the right to do that after our
defeat in the first war of independence
against the British in 1857 by the 1870s
the British prohibited Indians from
owning arms and carrying arms they made
it a crime and they allowed some
communities to carry arms I'll not
mention what those communities are
that's beside the
point so the question
is should India change its laws to allow
private citizens to own and carry
weapons does it make sense so let's ask
ourselves why we would need such a thing
hypothetically is it because the
government may go
tyrannical I'm not sure about that what
it would but if you had if you changed
the law and made
it legal for private citizens to own
arms weapons and to carry
weapons then it could make the defens
less not no longer defens less
who are the defenseless in India
generally it's the Hindus
right so it won't
happen won't
happen Okay j225 says what can I do to
improve my communication skills debating
abilities Etc I am a 17-year-old je
aspirant okay what's communication
skills what what are the different types
of communication there's verbal commun
communication there is nonverbal
communication there is written
communication there's public speaking
and so on so forth that's communication
mainly verbal and written so how do you
improve your let's say written
communication skills well you practice
writing what do you write do you like
write literature do you write po poetry
do you write a memoir do you write a
novel do you write technical literature
it's up to you what you going to write
you need to have if you want to improve
your written communication skills you
need to do daily writing a th000 words
2,000 words whatever or maybe you want
it to be objectoriented writing as in
the case like every your communication
should have a purpose your WR
communication have a purpose maybe how
to write better emails how to write
better essays or whatever then you
practice those things how do you become
a better cricketer a better fast bowler
you bowl every day 10 or 20 hours right
how do you become a better batsman you
play every day right you play let's say
500 balls every day you bat it's about
practice practice repetition repetition
repetition how do you become a better
musician you practice every day how do
you become a better writer you write
every day and every time you write it
has to have a specific purpose okay
today I'm writing I'm going to write the
drafts of let's say five emails or I'm
going to write three essays or whatever
it is it should be time bound it should
it should be like every day I'll write
this much these many words or I'll do
these many exercises in this much time 1
hour two hour whatever so it has to be
like that daily it's like you have to
put in the Reps repetitions like you do
in gym so that's how we do it for
written communication how do you improve
your verbal communication skills well
you practice once again you practice
practice practice so let's say you want
to become a better debater then you do
mock debates every day with your friends
with your classmates with your with your
parents with your siblings with whoever
you can find do it every day engage in
debates right if you want to become a
better public speaker well speak
assemble an audience of let's say three
of your siblings or cousins and give
them a speech and do it every day and if
you can find more people classmates
friends Etc do that so it's all about
repetition repetition practice practice
practice that's how you improve your
communication skills how do you become
better at communicating Okay so so if
you practice practice practice you'll
become more comfortable more comfortable
communicating let's say you want to
become you're scared of public speaking
scared of being on stage in front of
people then you have to repeatedly put
yourself in the situation that you're
scared of so that becomes second nature
and you you're no longer scared but how
do you
improve your performance so now you're
no longer scared you've done this 50
times 100 times you got used to it but
how do you improve your the quality of
your debate or writing or
whatever so that's for that you need to
know a lot you need to have a lot of
knowledge first of all so let's say you
have to give a
seminar in in in college okay and it's
about a topic that you know very little
about so you spend three days five days
researching the topic and you write down
the thing the outline and then you give
the seminar but then somebody asks you
questions and you you're stuck right so
to be able to be to be really
comfortable with this and do it well you
need to have not narrow knowledge in the
topic you need to have broad knowledge
in the topic that's how you can give
lots of examples from different
different angles and you genuinely
people can see that you know a lot about
the topic so you going to read a lot you
going to study a lot and you're write as
well a lot so that's how we do it it's a
process it's a journey you don't become
a great cricketer in a week's time it's
going to take two three years in the
same goes for these things communication
skills but you've got to do it regularly
you know to have a weekly schedule
monthly schedule whatever and you got to
religiously do what the various
exercises that you have set for yourself
and that if you do that then over over
just a period of a couple of months
three months you'll start seeing genuine
progress and that's how you do it all
the
best G of Aurora says what are your
views on studying computer science in
for the master's degree in Japan go for
it sir Japan has a tremendously good
education system one of the best in the
world Japan is at the Forefront of
Technology it's the most technologically
advanced nation in the world they are
tremendously proficient in Science and
Technology and Engineering so computer
science even if you are getting the
opportunity to study there I think you
should go for it absolutely the their
computer science degree will matter way
more than an Indian computer science
degree no question about it the Indian
education system is is trash it's
garbage you will learn nothing you'll
waste two years three years whatever it
takes master's degree two years right
you will end up learning nothing you
will end up acquiring no skills if you
are getting the opportunity to go to
Japan to do this go for it that's the
advice I give everybody if you're
getting an opportunity to study abroad
and if you can afford it go for it you
will actually end up learning something
as opposed to spending the same time in
an Indian
institution okay so I I would say
definitely you should go for
it feminist Slayer says how does
electricity how do electricity and
magnetism induce each other what kind of
books will you write we'll talk about
electr magnetism so there is something
called the electromagnetic
tensor which I will not talk about okay
so how do but it it comes from that and
it comes from special relativity special
relativity so if you look at a static
charge let's say I have an object which
is charged and it is static it's not
moving anywhere it's standing in front
of me so what will I perceive I will
perceive its electric
field but what if the static charge
starts
moving then that movement will produce a
magnetic field why is
that because moving
charges so that's what that's how it
affects the the the electromagnetic
tensor um it depends on the reference
frame that you are in if you are in the
same reference frame then you will only
perceive the magnet the electric field
but if you are in difference different
reference frame then you will perceive
an electric as well as a magnetic field
so if you if you have a wire in front of
you and an electric charge electric
current is flowing through it which is
electrons are flowing through it then
the movement of the charge is going to
create a magnetic field because if
electrons are going in that way it means
positive charges are flowing in this
direction essentially you can look at it
like that so it all comes from
relativity special
relativity and the the movement of
charges in special relativity it is what
induces the electric and magnetic fields
and it's all part of the electromagnetic
tensor so that's kind of how it works
you can also talk about farad is low and
all that but that is a more Basics basic
answer the answer lies in special
relativity if you want to genuinely
understand how it happens you've got to
study special relativity with
electromagnetism in context in the
context of electromagnetism or you have
to study electromagnetics in the context
of special relativity so you could study
the book
by uh who who's the guy I have it
somewhere here there's a book here but
uh maybe if you want I can look it up
and I can tell
you um yeah
Anish says I'm learning to play the
guitar any advice for me practice
practice look first of all I'll tell you
this you want to learn the guitar you
want to get good at that or learn any
skill if you practice once or twice a
week you will essentially get nowhere
you will make no great progress if you
practice once a week or twice a week so
ideally you should practice one hour a
day or two hours a day but let's say two
hours a day is too much even one hour a
day is great even if you do it like five
days a week one hour in each of these
five days you'll make good progress why
not do it six days why not do it seven
days whatever works for you so the more
you practice the more progress you will
make that's the first thing so you need
consistency of
practice secondly you have to decide
whether you want to be a rhythm player
Rhythm guitarist or a lead
guitarist okay you can be both
eventually but initially when you are a
beginner you to pick one lead or Rhythm
so let's say you pick Rhythm rhythm is
easier playing rhythm is easier you can
make very good progress very fast so
when you say that you'll become a rhythm
guitarist initially you'll learn how to
play rhythm guitar you have to learn the
chords the basic chords CDE EF g-c CDF G
right the basic major chords C Major D
major e f g a b major Etc then you learn
the minor codes you learn the open codes
you learn the bar chodes once you are
good with that with the code transitions
Etc you have to practice all that over
and over again your fingers will hurt
initially and so on you practice it over
and over again then you can start
learning the the major codes minor codes
then you start learning the augmented
codes the suspended CES there codes
there are hundreds of codes in that so
that takes time and those are more
complex finger shapes and all that but
that's where you bring out the real
essence of music and you got to that
takes time to master okay but the basic
code CDF
gab the major and minor codes minor
versions and the open and bar versions
you can Master pretty quickly maybe in a
couple of it depends it depends you
could do it in a month if you practice
uh often enough sufficiently so that's
about playing rhythm guitar you to
master all the chords and you to master
the code Transitions and then you to try
to play your favorite songs you look up
the cods online if you want and start
playing that so very soon you'll be
you'll start looking like you really
know what you're doing you're a good
guitarist you know and so that's how it
goes um that's rhythm guitar and then
you can start to uh try to figure out
the Cordes of a song then so and so so
song I heard what could the cords be
like and you can start looking into that
how to figure out how to how to reverse
engineer the cods of a song then when it
comes to lead guitar it's all about
playing scales there are all these
scales that you can learn mixian scale
and pentatonic scale and there are so
many scales Fran scale Etc but you begin
with the major scale and you learn the
various keys and so on and then you can
learn how to start learn how to
improvise on that and there are so many
there's a blue scale and so on so forth
so it's all about learning how to move
across the neck of the guitar there are
various systems the Caged system and so
on so you got to learn all that and so
when it comes to playing lead guitar
it's all about improvising it's all
about creativity it's all about
thinking and for some people it's
liberating and most people it's
difficult because you you know
creativity is hard uh but there's a
tremendous amount of scope for
exploration in lead guitar and then you
can play around with guitar tunings the
standard EAD GB tuning which is kind of
boring you could do dad Gad which is
beautiful you could do open C or open G
or whatever open F and so on so there's
a lot to do but start with the basics I
would say start with rhythm guitar learn
all the codes and when you are when you
are sufficiently comfortable you can go
and move into trying to play lead guitar
learning the scales and so on so forth
but main thing consistency as it goes
with any skill in the world you want to
become a better mathematician once again
practice practice practice practice you
want to become a better soccer player
practice practice whatever in life it's
a skill it applies to every skill
practice consistently and focus on the
basics first build a good foundation and
then move ahead build on top of the
Foundation that's how it goes with
everything all the best in your guitar
playing
journey and and maybe you could consider
hiring a coach or a teacher or taking
guitar classes perhaps uh that's
something many people do I am not aware
of how good or bad it is because I've
never had a guitar coach guitar teacher
I'm an entirely self-taught guitarist so
I don't know about that but maybe that
could also be beneficial yeah so and
there are guitar books Etc available
online how to read notation and how to
they will give you bunch of exercises
Etc and you could look at guitar YouTube
videos and so on so a lot you can do but
I would say focus on the basics the
fundamentals and consistent
practice rainbow says how many hours of
sleep is healthy for an adult human
being to function actively I believe the
average amount of sleep the average
person needs is eight hours roughly so
if you take the entire bulk of humanity
what 8 billion or whatever the number is
and you and and you calculate the
average of how much amount of sleep they
need ideally it will work out to be
around 8 hours and it depends on the on
each person some people need seven hours
some people need 10 hours and there are
some people called Elite speakers Elite
sleepers who need three4 hours so for
example Margaret Thatcher the former
prime minister of the
UK I believe she was okay she she was
fine with four hours of sleep and that
was enough for her and that was a
nightmare for for her staff because when
she was awake she would require
everybody to be present and working and
what if you needed 8 hours then it was a
nightmare for you but she needed four
hours apparently and it is said that
prime minister Narendra Modi needs three
or four hours of sleep only per night so
it depends some people are lucky that
they needs less sleep but most people
need eight eight hours of sleep and if
you let's say you need eight hours of
sleep and you're sleeping six
hours a day for a week or two it's going
to mess up your mind okay so get get
your sleep get the amount of sleep that
you need that way you will function
better and make better decisions and
overall your quality of life will be
better sleep is necessary sleep is very
important uh yeah so that's the deal and
with that I have done with today's
questions so let's take questions from
the live chat okay today I've I've I've
deliberately taken less questions from
the chat so that we can do about half an
hour of questions from the live chat an
goam says is mbbs from abroad better
than in India any educational
degree whether it's mbbs or or or or uh
MD or or whatever degree you can think
of BSC MSC ma ba mbbs whatever it is it
is better abroad I mean if you go to
Bangladesh or if you go to Somalia you
may not get a good degree
but um you go to Japan go to Korea go to
Australia go to the US go to Europe you
will definitely get much more value out
of your degree you will actually learn
the skills and and the and acquire the
knowledge that you that you're supposed
to acquire degrees in India are are
terrible okay and they don't count for
much abroad unfortunately I wish it was
not the way so I would say if you are
getting the opportunity to go abroad for
your degree and if you can afford it
definitely go abroad and do it
definitely okay
oh D shaing is here Welcome Back Sir so
the question is what are Singapore's
geopolitical concerns in this highly
unstable and unpredictable world what
kind of problems does it face from the
US and Malaysia good question yes so
where is Singapore I hope most Indians
would know where it is but let's see
okay Singapore is you
go east of the the Sea of Kalinga Bay of
Bengal
you go east of the Andaman sea you you
go into the malaka state and then you
come to Singapore Singapore is
essentially at the southernmost tip of
Malaysia okay that's what Singapore is
so Singapore is is is a nation state
it's an uh Island state so to say it is
named after what singapur right the city
of
lions so Singapore is a major economy
global economy it's an independent
nation it has a it has an important
port
uh and it's an ally of the US okay
Singapore is is a US Ally so what are
Singapore's geopolitical concerns
Singapore's geopolitical concerns is
that its economy should keep on doing
well it should remain connected with the
world it should not come under pressure
from any other Nation except the US and
so
on uh because it is such a small
geographically small
nation uh it is not that important from
geographical perspective geopolitically
it is an it is an important it has an
important strategic strategic location
it is kind of a
US proxy State you would say to a large
extent um so and they have a very good
Port where us aircraft carriers can dock
us submarines can dock so that gives the
US a very important base in the region
there is
that the Chinese kind of admire
Singapore they admired Le oneu but they
are aware of
Singapore's obviously they'll be aware
of Singapore being a pro us nation um so
the main concern for Singapore is that
it should remain independent and there
are no threats to its sovereignty as we
as we can see uh nothing from Malaysia
nothing from Indonesia
um they would want the economy to keep
doing well it's doing well it has this L
Fair economic model there is that uh so
it doesn't face any problems from
Malaysia from the perspective of the US
Singapore is a pro us nation and they
kind
of well do whatever the Americans mostly
tell them they don't go against us
wishes more or less there was this
famous case in the 80s or 90s there was
this American National who had uh being
charged of some some crime in Singapore
and he was sentenced to caning what is
caning you take a cane a stick and you
whack that person on their behind or on
their back and he was sentenced to a
certain number of lashes in Singapore
American citizen so the Americans uh got
very angry about this they and the the
US state department summoned the
Singapore Ambassador and gave that
person a tongue lashing apparently but
Singapore did not Bend to the US will
and that guy the American criminal was
in
caned as per the law so Singapore can
get away with small things like these
minor things like this but from a
geopolitical perspective they cannot go
against the the wishes of the us so that
is overall the situation of Singapore a
reasonably friendly country with India
lots of Indians live there leanu was a
friend of India you could say he was a
wellwisher of India and overall uh yeah
India and Singapore enjoy a good
relationship and then Singapore is named
it has an Indian name right singapur
so yeah that is the deal with
Singapore um gur aiz says why is the UN
failing to stop Wars and conflicts also
mu tips for UNSC I'm not sure what mu
stands for but what is the deal with the
UN the UN is an ineffective obsolete
organization the Security Council is
this Elite group of members who
represent the world order the balance of
power in the world at the end of of 1945
or from 1945 that is almost 100 years
ago the second world war is old ancient
history but they have Frozen in place
the geopolitical situation of the time
so it makes no sense I mean that's
that's useless and as is the case with
every multilateral organization the most
powerful nation in the organization
effectively controls and owns the
organization so it means the US controls
the UN essentially more or less to a
large extent and when the Americans
unleash a war somewhere the UN keeps
quiet when the Americans invaded Iraq
what happened did the U un intervene no
quiet so the UN is is ineffective it is
kind of useless and it's a waste of
money actually it's the US that's
running the show under behind the scenes
all over the world and I am not sure
what mu is so apologies for
that rah says I'm feeling very down I
lost IIT just for six marks all right
how is reservation fair I come from
lower middle class general family
General category family I have given
everything but I I can but I lost while
scst people got IIT with 90 marks less
the system in India is really
unfair true look I have nothing against
anybody from any category my only point
is the system should be
fair and if there's going to be
reservations those reservation should be
given on the basis of financial
situation not your cast or whatever it
is that that has to change and you
cannot have reservations going on
forever so reservations this the status
the situation the deal should be like
you will have reservations for x amount
of years let's say 10 years 20 years
whatever you want to make it 25 years
whatever the government decides and
those reservations should be given only
on the basis of your family's Financial
economic status not cast that's that's
wrong but that's how the system is
entrenched and now if the government
tries to change anything they will be
thrown out of power because they won't
get votes so that's where we are
horrible situation and then we have
cases like these like
Rahul uh people who got less marks are
going through while he isn't going
through it's not fair I completely agree
you need Merit in the country if you
want the country to do well otherwise
people like Rahul will justifiably
become disillusioned with the country
they will leave the country at the first
available opportunity and they will feel
bitter their whole life and they will
not come back you see rul I'll tell you
something the country doesn't the
country
hasn't you have been wronged but the
country isn't responsible the system is
responsible the system the
system is it's strangling the
country yeah uh so yeah you're feeling
very done what what can I say to I'll
say I'll say this look there's no person
in the world who has never faced any
setbacks in line everybody the most
successful people in the world have
faced tremendous
setbacks okay who are the most
successful people in the world think of
the greatest most most successful people
everyone has gone through all kinds of
hardships and setbacks and the greater
the person is the more hardships they
have faced and overcome so I'll say this
do not
become depressed I know it's a temporary
everything that you will feel down that
I gave by all and still I did not get
what I achieved what I wanted to achieve
okay it's a
setback you've got to stand up again and
move on so you need to have plan B plan
C if I don't get this I will do that if
I don't get that I will do this but you
always need to have Alternatives don't
put all your eggs in one basket
um life is long there's a long life
ahead of you as long as you stay as long
as you remain positive you remain
optimistic and you work hard and you
work smart by having multiple plans
you're going to do well in life so all I
will say is all the best be positive
don't allow yourself to be to feel
depressed and feel low for too
long don't indulge in
self-pity okay don't do that get back up
on your feet look at the options that
you have available for you if there are
no options that if you feel there are no
options you make
options nobody can stop you but you have
to be strong and resilient and you have
to go ahead with that so all the best
sir you will do well do well and prove
them
wrong
okay
um shaswat mukari
says Dal Lama succession China's
interest in it will the next Dal Lama be
from India as Tibet is occupied look I
think it is high time for his
Holiness the Dal Lama to uh declare what
is the succession going to be
like which means that he has to announce
he has to declare what his reincarnation
plans are like he is the Dal which means
that he can reincarnate at will that's
what it it says technically right so
does he plan to reincarnate in Tibet
which is under Chinese occupation does
he plan to reincarnate in India where
the free Tibetans live most of them or
does he plan to reincarnate somewhere
else or does he plan not to reincarnate
at all so he has to make an official
statement about this if he says I plan
to no longer reincarnate I am the last
Dal Lama if he makes That official
statement then anything the Chinese do
will be of no use because it won't be
recognized by Buddhists and
Tibetans so if the Dal Lama makes the
statement that I am the last Dal Lama I
will not reincarnate then even if the
Chinese try to appoint their own Dal
Lama it's going to be a fraud Dal Lama
it's going to be a fake Dal Lama nobody
will recognize that as as the true Dal
Lama if the Dal Lama says I will
reincarnate in India or reincarnate in
so and so country then once again the
Chinese attempt to take over the
institution will be regarded as a
fraud but if he makes no statement and
whenever he passes on to the next World
if when if it happens then the Chinese
will have the opportunity to hijack the
institution of the the Lama so it is
very important for China to own the
institution of the D Lama because they
are currently in occupation of Tibet and
to legitimize their rule over Tibet they
want a Chinese dalil Lama they will want
one a Chinese Dal Lama so uh it is
entirely up to his Holiness the the Lama
he should in my opinion it's entirely up
to him obviously who am I to tell him
but I think he should make an official
statement sooner rather than later about
this matter to set the matter at
rest geopolitical dub says why isn't
China commenting much on the Burma and
Bangladesh
situation because they are on the
receiving end their interests are being
eroded away they definitely had an
interest in
Bangladesh I think they sold some Naval
assets to Bangladesh ships or submarines
or something something they had sold at
some point in time so they were trying
to vuo Bangladesh to court Bangladesh
F's government but now the US has taken
over there's a puppet regime Mohammad
yunus is the puppet prime minister of
Bangladesh and U so Chinese whatever
influence they had is has evaporated in
Bangladesh when it comes to Burma the
military government was Pro China and
after
the and now there's this civil war going
on in in Burma the northern half of the
country more than the northern half is
in Rebel hands the rebels are all Cookie
and various other tribe people tribes
people all converted to Christianity all
uh
essentially us
agents so once again the Chinese uh
influence in Burma is evaporating
and as you can see the Chinese have
refrained from doing anything about this
because they don't want to uh enter into
any kind of conflict with the US so
China is very much on the back foot they
are on the receiving end their interests
have eroded away very rapidly and so
when you are in that situation you keep
quiet because you have already lost your
your influence your your power
projection in these countries and now if
you if you say say something about it
you will lose Fai too you will face
public humiliation right now you keep
quiet no at least you don't get
humiliated so that's what's happened the
Chinese are very big on Saving Face
they're saving face right
now okay what the questions the Big G
says I'm currently pursuing
BBA first year from a tire 3 college and
I currently have an opportunity of the
same from
IIM but the fees are very much more 22
lakhs the IIM fees are very high 22 26
I'm not sure yeah but you're saying 22
okay so what should you do look you've
got to be able to afford the the
education that you wish to
pursue um you cannot bankrupt yourself
or your family in the process of getting
a degree because your degree is going to
take you forward in your career only to
a certain extent at the end of the day
it's what you make of your life that's
going to matter look degrees in the long
run don't matter that much when you are
40 years old no one will care what
degree you got from
where maybe people still do in India but
in a few years time the situation will
change so I would say that
uh I I am if you it's it's it's
definitely one of the best institutions
in the country uh but if you can't
afford it I would say don't go for it
don't take a load and and and get
settled saddled with
death so do well so if you can't afford
it don't go for IIM the fees they're
very heavy I understand I totally know
that everyone knows that do your degree
from your college xavior or whatever it
is and uh study well and get a very very
high rank or whatever high
percentage and so so even if you're
doing your degree getting your degree
from let's say Tire 2 Tire three college
but if you have an excellent academic
track record then you will have a good
you will have good very good initial
career opportunities like job offers and
all that so I would say don't bankrupt
yourself in in in the pursuit of an IIM
degree that's what I would
say
Okay
um let's see what else do we have
others says I loved a girl earlier I got
to know she's married and she managed to
hide that from me what do I do now look
the way forward is clear you cannot be
in a relationship with a married person
it is unethical as far as I'm concerned
for you look everybody has a
different you know views on this it's
not illegal in India's in India system
having an extramarital affair is not
illegal so if you do go ahead with a
relationship with with this lady it
won't be something illegal but I would
say I I would see it as unethical it it
it's not something that fits
with the ethics and values of our
civilization but it's up to you uh what
I would recommend if you if you want to
know my
opinion is that you move
on you move on I mean somebody who was
married and she and she hid that from
you she was deceiving you you think
that's a person you want to be with
really a person who was deceiving
you move on find a better person that's
what I would
say
um then Ching says thank you for the
answer on Singapore which nation
according to you is not a proxy State
What problems will the US cause if they
if I decide to start my own sovereign
state in the future which nation is not
a proxy State India is not a proxy State
all other nations are in some way or the
other proxy of somebody else okay India
and China in the region are the two only
genuinely Sovereign Nations and Russia
in
Eurasia what is Eurasia go to the
map Eurasia is Europe plus Asia put
together if you take the entirety of
Eurasia from the British Islands from
Iceland and green okay from Iceland
British islands all the way to the
easternmost part of Asia
which is Japan and sakhalin Etc this
entire land mass is Eurasia okay
including the Saudi Arabian Peninsula
and so on in this entire landmar there
are only three fully Sovereign Nations
Russia China and India that's it all
other nations are in some way or the
other proxies of somebody else that's
how we go that's that's the deal What
problems will will the US cause if you
decide to start your own sovereign state
in the future first try to start a
sovereign state right you will need land
you will need
people right now you already have all
these nations you try to declare
independence somewhere the local
authorities will have something to say
about this but let's say you manage to
start a sovereign state somewhere well
if your state has resources that are
valuable Etc the Americans will be very
interested and then they will talk to
you and offer you
terms and if you are inconvenient they
will get rid of you so you got to be
careful about
that okay Anish asks a good question
Iran is Iran a proxy I would say that
Iran is not completely a proxy of
anybody else but Iran is greatly
beholden to China and Russia okay the
Chinese are investing the Chinese have
ined a 25e strategic uh partnership
agreement or something like that with
the the Iranians they're going to invest
about I don't know 40 or 400 billion
dollar worth of money in Iran in
exchange for Iran selling uh energy to
China at at significantly discounted
rates and Iran is under this immense
burden of sanctions from America from
the West it is cut off from the rest of
the world so Iran is heavily dependent
on China India is not in a position to
buy Iranian energy oil and gas because
of American pressure so Iran is heavily
dependent on China it's also heavily
dependent on
Russia and Iran is selling drones to
Russia and it is acquiring Russian
weapons and so on so Iran is heavily
dependent on China and Russia without
their support Iran will be destroyed so
you could
say that Iran is kind of a proxy of
China and Russia okay that is simply the
way the world works it is
Rie says well thank you so much sir
thank you appreciate
that love you
back mlen says saw a tweet recently that
the Dutch ate their prime minister can
you shed some light light on that I
think it's something that happened like
four 500 years ago I don't remember
which which year which century it was
but one of the Dutch Prime Ministers and
his brother was along with his brother
was lynched by a mob of Dutch people and
apparently they ate him like the crowd
eight parts of him
so weird but there you have
it you have
it uh
okay uh what other questions do we
have anurak Singh says why do some
people get success early and others do
not get success dis despite of the same
intensity in their work multiple
factors it's not enough to work hard
okay you have to be intelligent and make
the right choices you to work
smart so if you
are let's say in a certain industry
let's say you're in the IT industry okay
and you are in a certain
company and you work very
hard and you stay in the company for 5
years 10 years you will get very few
promotions and your salary won't change
much but let's say you change companies
every year every two years you will your
salary will increase rapidly very fast
and your ability to get promotions also
will increase very fast so you're
working equally hard both of the guys
both of the examples you're working
equally hard but in one case you your
salary your your your career graph Rises
very fast in the other case your career
graph
stagnates that's one example second some
people get
lucky and some people uh don't have a
lot of luck so for example if there are
two entrepreneurs who are in the same
field let's say once again you're in it
or you're in software or something and
one person hits upon the right idea and
and creates a product that has a
tremendous amount of
demand and there's nobody else in that
field then you get lucky and you make a
huge amount of money and you can retire
by the age of 25 or whatever it is right
you make a $100 million or something and
some somebody else may not stumble upon
that idea and you're trying other ideas
and you don't do well in that so there
are so many factors there is the luck
Factor there is the working smart factor
and so on so you've got to maximize your
chance for luck which means you would
take lots of try lots of ideas do lot
lots of things if you're an entrepreneur
if you are in in in a salary job you're
an employee then you have to approach
the thing very strategically very
systematically don't St get stuck to the
same company for 5 10 years move to a
different company every one or two years
that way and and do well in that one
year or two years you're in this company
so you can demonstrate your skills and
your values and and and the value that
that you bring to the company that you
are trying to go into and that's what
you do that's the reason okay there are
so many factors involved in this and you
to be really smart about that to
succeed
okay paulomi says what are the akashik
records
I'm apparently it's it's the it's the
record of all the good things and bad
things you've done and all all the all
the actions you've taken across
lifetimes so it's it's the it's the
register in the cloud let's say of all
the actions that you've taken over your
multiple lifetimes and the merits and
the demerits of your actions so that is
how your karma is decided that's
apparently what akashik records is I am
not an expert in this by any means so
that is my very limited and rud mentary
understanding of what the akashic
records
are
um ramachandra namaha says how does
Jupiter have gravity even if it's a ball
of gas it's a gigantic ball of gas with
a tremendously large
mass okay uh let's let's take a look at
Jupiter let's go to Google let's Google
Jupiter and see the images okay and I'll
explain the scale the the the scale of
Jupiter
Jupiter and uh let's see
here so this is what Jupiter looks like
let's take a big image size large okay
and here's an image why is it not large
enough come on this
one or this one so you can see that
Jupiter has this red spot right this
gigantic red spot it's called the red
the red spot of Jupiter and that spot
itself is is a big big storm and it is
large enough to to engulf two
earth-sized objects that's how large
Jupiter is okay and the density of
Jupiter for the most part
is is similar or greater than the
density of water especially as you go
deeper into the atmosphere of Jupiter
towards the center so it has so even gas
molecules have mass one hydrogen
molecule a very small amount of mass but
Mass adds up right Mass adds up you take
one liter of liquid hydrogen it has mass
it's it has
weight and this is kind of liquid
hydrogen especially if you go deeper
inside so it is gigantic its scale is
immense and that's why it has tremendous
amount of gravity largest planet in the
solar system right and it does a
tremendous job of saving us from
asteroids and all because it has
gathered sheered a large number of
asteroids in in its lrange points the
Trojan
asteroids and there you have
it yaj Singh says does India have
Megaton yield bombs well if we have we
will not talk about them
so and that's that's classified
information that people like me and you
are not supposed to know about so I
don't know okay but yeah
Pro we may we may have it perhaps or may
not maybe not I have no idea there's no
way for me to know
that endan says drdo has already
developed a 73 Kon engine why can't drdo
design a twin engine aircraft using that
engine can deep State like okay let's
take one question can mix two totally
oil and water like questions okay the
new the kilon 73 Kon engine we obviously
talking about the C engine right that
has been development in development
since 3000 BC or
something kidding you know what I mean
uh and the institution in in charge of
that is the GT the gas gas turbine
research establishment in Bangalore I
think so that's where the development is
is is happening now apparently the
output the thrust of this C engine is
roughly 70 or so kilo
newtons and the re requirement is that
it should be 95 or something so what
you're suggesting makes sense instead of
a single engine aircraft have a double
engine aircraft with 270 K engines so
the total thrust is 140 kons which is
more than sufficient it's a powerful
enough thrust if you look at the Rafal
okay let's take a look at the Rafal
let's let's Google this
okay let's go to Google and let's find
out what is the trust of the Rafal
engines the Rafal is a twin engine
aircraft Rafal
jet okay the soul Rafal so what's the
engine that it has let's search for
engine blah blah blah blah blah blah etc
etc what engine does it use it was using
those f44 engines blah blah
blah pending the availability of this
and Z SN
snma M8
let's let's quickly find out okay it has
the snma m88 engine it has two of these
now the snma m88 what is its
thrust let us
[Music]
see uh the thrust that it
has
thrust 73
Kon
as for light okay so the the one that
powers the the is 73 kons which is more
or less similar to now let's see the
Kary engine shall we so the this engine
that powers the Rafal has a Thrust of
73 kilo newtons now let's see the cavy
engine cavy engine what is the thrust
that this guy
produces thrust thrust
thrust maybe it's overweight or
something thing but
[Music]
uh okay 70 to 75 K so it's kind of what
the rafal's engine does so why can't we
develop a twin engine aircraft with two
of the cavar engines the question is is
the Cav engine too heavy is it too
overweight ET that all we have to see
look into of which I don't have time to
do right now because it will take up my
time here and it'll waste your time me
researching all that but yeah it seems
to have sufficient thrust
for us to create a twin engine aircraft
and use the covery engine does it have
the proper after bur burner capabilities
does it have a significant amount what
is a thirst to weight ratio all that
stuff we have to look into but I think
it is already able to produce a
sufficient thrust well at least the same
thrust as the engine that Pro that
powers the dool
Rafal so uh I'm not sure what the hold
up is is it like we only have a
requirement for a single engineer
and we want a 95
K engine on that I'm not sure what the
deal is or is it that the the covery
engine is too large is is it overweight
do we need to miniaturize it further so
there could be certain technical
considerations why it is still not seen
as a viable
engine but why don't we address them we
have great
Engineers the engineers at ISRO do great
work the jet engine is a whole different
set of things but
we should be able to solve this I mean
it's taking too long don't you think and
as a result we have to buy American
engines those f404 or whatever those
engines are and the Americans can apply
all kinds of pressure on India by
delaying the deliveries or withholding
deliveries all kinds of pressure I think
it's high time for us to become
self-sufficient in the field of jet
engines and if this the Cav engine is
taking longer by jet engine technology
from the French or the Russians or
whoever pay whatever you need to pay and
acquire the technology but I'm sure it's
easier said than done so that is a deal
that is a
deal shaswat mukari says who is easy to
deal with Kamala or Trump trump you not
a look I think Mr Trump is better to
deal with from India's
perspective uh
Kamala Kamala is just like Biden okay he
may be a good person bad person I'm not
sure what it doesn't matter she won't
really be in power even Trump won't be
100% in power but at least he's his own
man and he has very clear views about
everything and and he and he has a great
equation with with India with Prime
Minister Modi Kamala I remember when
Once when Mr Modi had visited the
US Kamala was lecturing him about
democracy and human rights and blah blah
blah standing right next to him and she
was lecturing him Kamala is going to be
a problem if she comes to power if she
is elected and if she comes to office
not power no one's in power okay so I
think it'll be better for India if if Mr
Trump comes back to the office of the US
president to the White House and it will
be more problematic if Kamala stays in
the White House and becomes president of
the US this
time U mclen says where's Joe Biden he
has disappeared from the earth it's like
he never existed maybe he never did I
don't know I don't know where he is uh
Joe Biden Joe Biden he doesn't matter
he's never mattered he was never really
in power
right uh tat Tonga says it's okay to ask
this late I'm still answering for a
while do you think there should be any
educational or experiential
qualification for Indian politicians
look the education system is garbage in
India so you may have a PhD but you may
still be dumb
as what's the polite term dumb as dumb
dumb as a doo let's
say so you may have a there are pH there
are so many PHS in this country I don't
know what their IQ is it must be less
than room temperature okay so easy to
get a PhD in this country especially
through the wrong means in the
humanities and whatnot yeah my God so
educational qualifications if you have
uh some kind of requirement in India it
makes no difference whatsoever then
everybody will start acquiring degrees
okay all kinds of degrees if you make it
mandatory to have a certain amount of
education qualifications these guys will
purchase degrees degrees are available
for sale in this country that's that's
the tragedy of this country of the
education system I think everybody who
is in the academic field knows that
there are lots of universities where you
can essentially purchase
degrees okay without naming
anyone so there's no point doing this
but yeah there should be I mean
that's the that's the deal about
democracy everybody is equal so
everybody has the right to run for
election so yeah it doesn't really work
that way especially in the context of
the current Indian education
system ideally if you have a good
education system I think there should be
some kind of entrance exam you can
become a politician and stand for office
only if you can clear this exam it
should not be some stupid exam in which
you to write like 10 essay type answers
and all that should be an exam that
actually gorges
whether you are genuinely worthy of
standing of of running for some kind of
elected office public office in the
country so
yeah
uh Ravi tan says can we Flex by testing
a nuke that has a yield in excess of 100
megatons right now we can't Flex testing
any nuke not even a 20 kilot nuke okay
we
can't you can't we can't test right now
the moment you test you will have
sanctions imposed upon you so not
happening Grim zad says do you ever see
India transitioning slowly into an
imperial dictatorship I'm completely
sick of democracy and it doesn't work
for us not in the current scenario not
not in the foreseeable immediate or
medium-term future not not happening not
going to happen the current system is
very deeply entrenched and everyone who
comes to power through the system
worships the system because if this
system brought you to power brought you
to power why will you not want the
system to
continue so I don't see India
transitioning into an imperial democracy
without some kind
of very very radical
event like genuine people's Revolution
or
something which is easier than done so
and and revolutions are dangerous
because they are
destructive and they they cause a lot of
damage more
usually more harm than good so I don't
see India transitioning into an imperial
dictatorship what by what means could
that happen well a plausible way of that
happening is that somebody comes to
power as prime minister with a gigantic
majority and then decides not to leave
office and the military
cooperates and
the system also cooperates well the
system is deeply
well won't work not anytime soon I know
why you're sick of democracy
yeah D Singh says can India play the
role of a mediator in the Russia Ukraine
war thank you so look India is uniquely
positioned as a bridge between East and
West how is India uniquely positioned
India can engage with Russia with a
great amount of comfort in a great
amount of trust Vis A Russia and India
similarly India can engage with the West
the US Etc with a great amount of
comfort and Trust so we have that we are
in this unique position that we are the
only nation that has this equation with
both sides East and West us and Russia
so yes if both sides want mediation
India is ideally positioned to be the
ideal mediator so India can play the
role but only if both sides desire
Russia has said that it wants to
negotiate it wants
diplomacy the Americans don't want
diplomacy they they want this war to
continue
so that's why India is not currently in
a position to mediate but if the
Americans agree for a diplomatic uh if
the Americans agree to explore a
diplomatic solution then India could be
possibly the ideal mediator between the
two sides
okay VII Manar says why is Mr Gandhi Mr
mandas Gandhi called the father of the
oldest civilization this also belittles
the contribution of other Freedom
Fighters as well why has nobody ever
challenged this in the Supreme Court
Supreme cour look I don't think he's
officially the father of of the
nation and he is the father of the
nation not of the civilization I mean
whoever calls him the father they call
him the father of the nation not the
father of the
civilization and India as a nation state
came into existence only in 1950 right
when India becomes a India became a
republic in 1947 India became a Dominion
of the of the UK of the British Empire
it's in 1950 that India became a
republic
so so that's when India became a nation
state and uh those
who who rever Mr Gandhi they call him
the father of the nation uh and I don't
think it's an official title so there's
no challenging it because it's not
official but yeah the narrative has been
constructed that Mr Gandhi is solely
responsible for India's freedom and he
magically got us freedom because of
nonviolence all that is well you know
how it works it's all narrative it's all
propaganda and it also definitely
belittles the contribution of the
freedom fighters who actually died okay
who actually died I mean thousands tens
of thousands
Millions were murdered by the British in
the aftermath of
1857 the British killed at least 10
million Indians in
retribution okay nobody remembers those
people our people who died for us no one
remembers them today but Mr Gandhi Mr
Gandhi father of
nation so I'm glad people are now
beginning to wake up and beginning to
realize what the context of India's
Freedom struggle is it was a bloody fre
Freedom struggle so many of our people
died and what about all the 100 plus
million Indians who were starved to
death in artificially engineered famines
those are also victims of our freedom
struggle uniting victims but certainly
victims no one remembers them them why
is there no day of Remembrance in
India for the victims of the British
engineered genocide of Indians why is
there no day of remembrance of
that but we remember the people who
really did not do
much
sadly
so
uh okay let's take one or two more
questions um where is it where is it
where is it I saw something and it
disappeared okay okay let's see this
herel mikar says many US companies
Outsource their work to India many such
companies pay Indians in US dollars is
this transfer of US dollars to India
helping the US the Indian economy to
some extent it may but what you want is
Investments of billions of dollars
hundreds of billions of dollars B
billions so a little bit of money
trickling in through the through these
transfers of money to various Indian
employees it doesn't make a huge dent in
the Indian GDP what you want is large
scale foreign investment Greenfield
Investments and whatnot in the Indian
economy and so that is what makes a
genuine difference so this these little
amount of money coming in through each
person it it I'm sure it contributes
something a few drops in the ocean but
overall it doesn't make a gigantic
difference it makes a small difference
for
sure
okay G of ARA says please explain about
planet 9 in the solar system so when I
was a curious when I was growing up
planet 9 was Pluto but now Pluto is no
longer a planet apparently some
bureaucratic P minded person decided
that Pluto is no longer a planet it's a
minor planet or a dwarf planet so we now
officially have only eight planets in
the solar system and then there is talk
of planet nine so what is this so if you
look at the orbits of the various
objects in the solar system they are all
aligned in the same plane right the same
plane Mercury Venus Earth Mars Jupiter
Saturn Uranus nept Uranus and Neptune
they're all in the same plane Pluto is
kind of weirdly eccentric Uranus is a
weirdly uh oriented uh rotational
axis but more or less in the same plane
but there are other objects beyond the
orbit of Pluto the minor planets the
planetoids the planet symbols Etc that
are very strangely skewed orbits not
along the plane of rotation of the solar
system but but very strangely aligned
okay very strangely oriented at sharp
degrees to the plane of Orient of
rotation of the solar system that kind
of tells you that there is something out
there that is affecting these objects
and and and it has skewed their orbits
and it if you calculate all of this
through various means that you have in
Celestial Dynamics and all that it tells
us that there seems to be something out
there that we not able to see it's a
large gravitating object which is
tugging away at these small objects over
there and changing their orbits and
that's why their orbits have been
changed and and skewed in that way so
that is what has given rise to the
hypothesis that there is a an unknown
large massive Planet out there that we
have not discovered yet in the far outer
reaches of the solar system and that's
what what we call Planet 9 some people
call it Planet X as well but Planet 9 so
the search is on but we have not
discovered it yet solar system is
gigantic and U the further you go away
the less Light reaches you so if you if
you are let's say hypothetically
standing on the surface of Pluto and you
look at the sun it looks like a big star
it doesn't look like this ball of fire
it looks like a very bright star and you
go further away from from Pluto the
smaller the sun looks and the less of
the Sun's light reach is there so if
even if you have a large earth-sized
planet let's say way out there in the
solar system it will receive almost no
light compared to what we receive and
that's why it'll stay so dark so it's
very hard to detect it and that's the
deal so maybe there's a planet out there
maybe it's a primordial black hole who
knows what it is there seems to be
something out there but it's not been
discovered yet the search is on but
right now we are empty-handed so that is
what is planet nine
okay and let's take one more
question
um let's take one more
question then shopping says okay last
question for today the domain of
geopolitics is really dense even though
I've been dabbling in it since 2018 what
efforts should I diligently undertake to
develop my understanding of geopolitics
further the right way to understand
geopolitics is to study a lot of
history for a decade or two
that's when all the patterns start start
to make sense and you will see see that
history occurs in Cycles you study a lot
of history not just your own country's
history but world history it will study
the rise and Decline and fall of Empires
and dynasties for you to see how various
military campaigns happen why do Wars
happen and how do Wars go and so many
things so there's so much involved in
this there's human psychology involved
this human nature involved in this so
you study a lot of history that's when
you start seeing all the patterns and
cycles of human of of human history and
then you can start extrapolating those
patterns into the future on the basis of
various principles or you could take my
geopolitics course which is linked Down
Below in which I have you know it's
called geopolitics from first principles
in which I have explained geopolitics on
the basis of principles that I have
understood from my study of history so
you could do either of those so that's
how
you could develop your understanding of
geopolitics and with that we are at the
end of today's session thank you so much
for all your
questions and we will do many more of
these in the coming
weeks and somebody is complaining I
ignored that question look there are a
million people over here and I cannot
take everyone's question so I apologize
in case you are upset that I could not
take your question but try your luck
next time and hopefully I can take I can
take it next time all right so thank you
so much have a good day good night
Wherever You Are and keep asking
questions and keep raising your
standards always thank you see you soon
bye